this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
c-radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society by IEEE software
Magazine online at computer.org software
hello everyone my name is
Phil educator at twilio where he helps
students to learn with twilio Quest
twilio's educational game previously he
was a program manager for GitHub
education and the developer Advocates at
PayPal welcome to the show Joe hi there
thank you so much for having me
the topic of today's show is developer
relations and this is of course a role
from your biography we know that you are
familiar with but knows everyone might
actually know what developer relation
what it even means so what does that
mean what relations do developers have
with whom
yeah sure so I mean this is a bit of a
complicated answer which is pretty much
the best way to start but I guess most
simply per developer relations is
business function which helps companies
reach developers whether those
developers be customers of the company
say to developer facing product or
stakeholders for example if you have a
developer platform like slack for
example where they want developers to
build apps so in both of those cases
people who do the developed relations
role are trying to help that company
reach and build relationships with
Developers and I think there are two
terms here that might play a role
sometimes people call themselves
developer Advocate but also we hear the
term developer evangelist is that the
same thing yes so this is another area
where the answer is complicated
developer evangelist was kind of the
original title and that meant someone
who you know would go out into software
communities on behalf of a company and
Advocate to developers and talk to
developers and spread the word of the
product to developers and over the years
there's kind of been a trend change to
developer Advocate and that is largely
honestly in my view because the word
evangelist has some religious
connotations that not are not
necessarily appropriate for every
Community but there's also kind of been
antilio is an example of this an idea
that actually those are two different
roles where evangelists are more about
outward messaging and Advocates more
about bringing developers concerns back
into the company so some some companies
do operate evangelists and Advocates as
two separate roles other places it's
just kind of a trend change where
they've wanted to keep up with you know
the times and choose a globally
applicable word
so if we are in a situation where we
have these two roles is it like an
evangelist is more pre-sales and maybe a
developer Advocate is more helping
people to actually use the products
yeah yeah I'd say that's pretty accurate
yeah evangelists tend to be about
awareness they tend to be top of the
funnel so helping developers you know
understand that this company exists and
it has developer products and what they
can do with the tools and then Advocates
are very often very integrated into the
product feedback life cycle so they'll
be out with developers ensuring that
their feedback gets incorporated into
future iterations of the product making
sure the developer experience is good
they will often you know still be some
both roles will have a big education
component so both roles will support
developers in implementing the company's
solution but yes I think that where they
play into the sales life cycle is a very
good way of looking at the difference
so why does this rule exist what do
companies typically need developer
advocates for
so mostly the I guess the meme of the
popular conception of why developer
relations exists is that developers are
often thought of as hard to market to I
don't necessarily agree with this
personally but that is the popular
conception the idea is that if you are
marketing to like technical people where
technical means you know that's soft
they're into software they're into
software development you need people who
have some understanding of that domain
in order to speak their language in
order to communicate effectively with
them and so you end up with essentially
technical marketing and so that is kind
of you know where developer relations
comes in over time developer relations
has taken on lots of other roles and you
kind of often see it essentially acting
as like the glue for an organization
that needs to address developers where
developer relations will interface with
every Department that interface with
those developers and act as kind of the
technical spokesperson so developer
relations may get involved in marketing
they may get involved in sales they'll
get involved in content and in products
and where they they are you know acting
as the developer within the company so
it pops up in lots of places lots of
different roles as I said the the main
reasons a company will need developer
relations is if they are pursuing
developers as either a customer or as
part of a platform play so if you're
selling to developers you need to be
able to often selling to developers or
marketing to developers means empowering
developers to to build on top of your
apis or your software your sdks and so
that means technical content and equally
if you are doing a platform play so you
want developers to build on top of your
product uh you need a lot of you know
you need to inspire them to say that hey
this is a place you can build your
business this is the place you can build
your app on top of and so that also
requires a developer in the seat
so the type of companies that would
typically have such a role are companies
that allow developers to build upon
their platforms so they might have and
as already said an API or an SDK there
is a page for developers to interact
with with their Cooling and therefore
you want to support them in doing that
effectively and with joy that is correct
yeah there is there is some Nuance there
in that we are increasingly seeing
companies that Target developers as a
consumer also have developer relations
so GitHub is quite an interesting
example of this GitHub is a product
obviously developers use as you know a
product we come and put our code on
GitHub and that's not really a platform
play right like that is US using it as a
consumer but then they also have an API
and they also have things like GitHub
actions and a way to build apps on
GitHub and so GitHub developer relations
kind of plays between both where you
know they're encouraging developers to
Target GitHub as a platform for their
own applications but then also they are
just you know evangelizing the use of
GitHub as a product with developers so
you do kind of get both ends of that now
and there are typically a devrel falls
on a spectrum between like are you a
product or are you a platform and what
you what you need from a devrel depends
on where on that Spectrum you fall yeah
interesting so sometimes you might
mainly be
wanting developers who use your tools
even if they might not customize the
tools with the API something like GitHub
or maybe also slack could be an example
of that or Discord where you also want
developers to be your customers so you
want to make sure your product like
looks cool and has features that
developers want but also you want to
support them and building on your
platform
exactly jetbrains is another really
interesting example of that actually
let's move on to what the job actually
looks like so I think most of the
audience would know if you want to be a
programmer or if you want to be an
architect these are the skills that you
might have but how does that work for a
developer relations person what type of
skills like are you like a programmer
are you like a salesperson
how do you define yourself and what are
the skills that you you would need if
some people that are listening might
consider becoming such a role what are
the skills you need for that
sure so I think it's probably easiest to
start with the developer Advocate the
developer evangelist role this is the
role I think most people have
experienced Endeavor Elm and when you're
looking at those roles a lot of skills
depending on the company come into it
but often said there is that aspect of
communication being out there in
developer communities
um is a big prominent part of those
roles so public speaking will often be
part of that ability to not only you
know be confident and communicate a
message while on stage but be able to
craft a narrative so to take you know
your company's product and think of
stories you can tell around that and
that doesn't always necessarily need to
be product focused lots of developer
advocates for example I had a talk I
used to do at PayPal which was about
some cool engineering that was happening
within within PayPal that was completely
orthogonal to use of the product for a
developer but you know it was an
interesting story and showed that you
know we were doing some really cool
technical stuff and so that's
interesting to developers so the ability
to build narratives and tells compelling
stories is really important often
developer Advocates will be involved in
content creation of all kinds so
traditionally that's been blog posts and
social media content and so again being
able to tell Amazing Stories in a
written format it's really useful in
being able to make an entertaining but
educational content pieces is very
important for blog work and over the
course of the pandemic video work has
taken a more important place as
especially live streaming has taken on a
lot of importance versus where we used
to do a lot of in-person stuff so that's
developer advocacy lots of other roles
depending on the size and sophistication
of the relations department will fall
into devrel so you know you've read out
program management it's the title I've
had in the past there's increasingly
developer focused programs that get run
by devrel some departments incorporate
documentation and other technical
education roles but I think those are
probably more familiar to a lot of folks
I think the one that will probably be
most novel is the developer Advocate
role so the ability to you know take
your development skills and share those
primarily what you're looking at what
does a job look like like day to day it
seems like it's a very very tight job
where you do many different things like
blogging going to conferences doing live
streams how does that work like how do
you organize the work you do like
there's no avoiding it it is chaotic
often you know in the peak of my times
of developer Advocate my day-to-day has
been defined by the conference season so
you get very used to like for example
Octobers and novembers are doomed that's
when all the big conferences are you
just get used to living out living on a
plane again that's changed in more
recent years but yeah it's very driven
by the community and the community's
needs I say it's a very reactive role
you know you will often be responding
not only to what the your developers
need and what the developers in your
community need and what they're doing
with conferences and events but also you
know what's coming out of your company
so developer Advocates are very busy
this time of year because lots of big
developer facing companies tend to do
their big product conference in in this
time right we've got GitHub Universe
twilio signal all these kind of things
and that's when the big announcements
come out and so that's from the blog
posts and the talks need to be done and
so it is a very reactive role one of the
tensions I think and I you know I
imagine we'll talk about this is keeping
up your proficiency as a developer
yourself that's something that a lot of
developer Advocates worry about honestly
because you know there isn't necessarily
always time to sit down and you know
churn out a lot of code you'll often be
working on samples and demos and you
know piece bits and pieces for blog
posts but when you are you know on the
content production Pipeline and
traveling so much it can be can be hard
to find that time and so that's
something that you'll often try and make
for time for depending on the season so
earlier in the year it's easier to make
time to sit down and like work on the
SDK and that kind of stuff right yeah
it's chaos
yeah that sounds really challenging and
how do you know especially given all
those different tasks we have how do you
know if you're doing well right if
you're a developer then at least there's
some metrics like we have so many users
or we have so much traffic so many
request gloves or features added when
are you doing well how do you know that
this is again another like a question
that Deborah loves to ask itself all the
time which any Deborah people listening
to this will know is a particular sore
point of mine there's lots of ways of
measuring depth rail depending on what
your product slash platform is it can be
a little bit easier so you know if
you're a developer Advocate there are
all kinds of quote-unquote vanity
metrics that you can use just to you
know get a rough idea of how things are
going day to day how many people were in
my talk how's my views on my YouTube
video going that kind of thing but
ultimately like actual success is going
to depend on the instrumentation you
have around the actual product and the
funnel for the product like if you work
on if you're a devil working on a
product that has a free trial mechanism
or a promo code driven mechanism where
you can give you know where you can have
attribution for a developer that signs
up due to something you've done that's
obviously a far less stressful situation
to be in it's much easier to point to
your results unfortunately that's not
the nature of a lot of products there's
some really cool tooling out some really
cool measurement out there I think one I
always quote is the Microsoft Azure team
have really good tracking on their
documentation and so they actually know
a very granular level or have known in
the past I don't know this is still true
have known in the past at a very
granular level how many signups to
Microsoft Azure come from documentation
written by their developer advocacy team
right and so they have like that level
of detail and so yeah the approaches
vary one of the things you read at my
bio was the GitHub role and git student
developer pack that was kind of a dream
role from a metrics perspective because
you know we had a student-focused
product it was a student discount and
that was the primary number right
everything we did funneled down to that
number and so you know what we were
always looking for was hey here's the
mechanism by which we we move that
number forward and so everything comes
down to this North Star metric finding
that North Star metric wherever you go
is kind of the defining difficulty of a
developer relations role internally I
would say yeah that was going to be my
next question right but this is also a
question that matters for developers
there also you might think are we
counting the number of users or are we
counting the number of users that stick
with us for more than one month so I
understand and generally it's really
hard but I do still want to know from
you what is the process to define the
Northern Star is this a thing you do you
put together with like the board of the
company or with the developers how does
that work that process of deciding this
sure yeah and it's gonna hopefully be a
very collaborative process in practice
it's often not but again it comes down
to what is the company building and how
to developers factor into that sales
cycle right so if you want to talk about
a platform company so you're talking
about you know a slack or a Discord as
we said the ultimate goal there is that
you know developers build an application
on top of that platform that's a
decision that's very driven by the
developer right like you know it might
be a company that's building the
application but the choice to you know
Implement against slack is probably very
driven by a developer and so developers
are very important in that sales cycle
and so in that case you might find that
you can you know that metrics like
number of developers reached are
slightly more impactful and Powerful
because the developer has an outsized
impact on adoption in that case in other
cases you know if you have a more
Enterprise focused product you might
find that the developer actually has
let's say in the adoption so actually a
good example this is video games so
video games you know really technically
intensive development process but they
have very long development cycles and
once they've locked into a technology
they can't readily change that
technology and there's a period of time
where like they need to choose what
they're going to build the next game on
and once that's done it's a short period
of time once that's done that's done
it's not super useful to Market to
developers in video games because they
don't have a lot of influence on the
technology being used you can't you know
their your window of opportunity to get
to a developer and influence them is
very very small and so in that case you
know reaching developers or number of
developers reached isn't a super useful
metric right so really and this is I
think where a lot of companies have
their first stumbling blocks of devrel
is they don't often ask or don't often
analyze very intensely like hey what is
the role developers actually play in in
potential adoption or go or no go on our
products developer relations is very
trendy and so it's very easy to say like
hey everyone has developers everyone
hires developers but developers don't
have equal power in every company right
like the web I think the webs and apis
uh like that industry that part of of
tech has really popularized developer
relations because you know building
websites developers do have a lot of say
in adoption just generally speaking but
that doesn't necessarily apply to
everywhere where you you know you might
be looking at employing developer
relations and so when it comes to you
know actually working out like how do we
define success really the question is
what is the value of an individual
developer come into your platform and
then you have whether successes more
developers or deeper relationships for
developers all comes from that right if
it's a slows if it's you know high if
developers have a lot of power in
adoption going for many many developers
and just getting the word out as wide as
possible is a pretty viable strategy if
if you need to you know reach a high
level person in the company and you
might want to establish close
relationships and work for more ctOS or
Architects than you know individual
front-end devs right does that make
sense yeah so it's very much ties also
to what the mission of the company is
right because indeed you might attract
many developers oh I make this very fun
plug into slack or something but is that
going to lead to a paying customer or
are you just spending energy of The
Advocates or hobbyists that are making
fun things but are not necessarily
leaning to more customers so it's I
imagine that it's also very very tied to
what your business model is
yes exactly yeah and I think a really
actually fascinating example of this is
um is Spotify so Spotify have a API
platform you can use the Spotify API you
can do a bunch of cool stuff with it but
like what are the businesses actually
building on top of Spotify as you know
like building their business on top of
Spotify it's things like integrated
smart speakers and like dashboards for
cars and like you know in those
Industries
um
I mean first of all like they're
adopting Spotify for reasons that are
completely orthogonal to the developer
experience like they have to integrate
Spotify regardless right so whoever a
developer likes the API or not is it
relevant
um the legal situation you know the the
legal and copyright surroundings of
integrating a music provider into those
systems again also removes a lot of
power from the developer making that
choice
um and then you know hardware and
Automotive are both Industries where a
developer doesn't have a lot of decision
making power so like that's a great one
where I think a really interesting
example of like Spotify investing in
devrel and they have a public API
um and the devrel folks can you know go
and get a bunch of developers building
on it but does it necessarily
enable more people to build with Spotify
right or like does it influence the type
of companies that are building with
Spotify probably actually not
um
still a good thing for them to be doing
it's still very you know devrel can you
know having a good public facing API can
do wonders for all kinds of things from
the company especially hiring if you are
seen to be a developer friendly company
it's a lot higher a lot easier to hire
Developers
so that's never valid valid part of it
but yeah it's a difficult question
yeah that is interesting that
perspective of hiring this might be
another reason right why companies have
developer relationships not necessarily
to show this is how you build on a
platform or this is how cool our
platform is but more to show we are a
company that cares about developers and
therefore can work for us right is this
also something that is generally seen as
the responsibility of devrel or is this
like the in the HR department and this
is entirely out of your scope typically
yeah again it can vary it's another like
over uh overlap with Talent is another
is another thing that some devil teams
do and some devil teams are built around
this this principle so you know I just
mentioned Spotify there and their API
um Spotify have a have a developer
facing product called backstage which is
an internal tool
um that they uh they built for their own
usage and then they started evangelizing
outside in a similar way to Facebook and
react and they've got a devrel team for
backstage and you know that's nothing to
do with spotify's product that's purely
we've built a cool developer tool we
think it's good it's good for the
company for developers to think it's
good so let's help Advocate it so you
know that's a developer relations team
that
um has kind of been founded with that
idea that you know there's they they are
probably mostly a brand positioning
thing right and you can arguably say the
same in many ways about like you know
the any developer Advocates who work on
something like react like react is react
is not related to Facebook's business as
a social media company right like it
doesn't get more people to log into
Facebook and upload photos of their dogs
um but Facebook needs a lot of
developers
um react is very very popular and has
had a huge impact on the developer
ecosystem so being a developer Advocate
working on react you are primarily
working on Facebook the brand and so you
will you will have develop relations
teams but that is the core premise that
is what you are doing and it's pretty
clear from the outside when you go to
work on a team like that that's like oh
I'm not working on the product that pays
the bills I'm working on a product that
helps the company that helps us build a
company that pays the bills right
imagine people want to become a
developer relations person how do you do
that and maybe we can start with your
path like did you go from being a
programmer to being an advocate how was
your process and and how is the typical
process into far as you know that
um my path is really weird and probably
not generally applicable
um my path is via hackathons which isn't
isn't itself uncommon so for those who
aren't aware hackathon is kind of like a
programming Adventure Marathon so
typically you'll spend multiple days
um in a room with a couple of hundred
other people just building Cool Stuff
um there may be prizes there may not be
um you know this Community Driven
hackathons coming during hackathons I
was very involved in student hackathons
when I was in university
um but also used to go to some
professional hackathons and one of those
was PayPal's hackathon which no longer
exists but was called battle hack and
battle hack was kind of a World Cup
setup so they'd hold it in every city
um and then they'd fly the winners out
to their office in Silicon Valley where
you'd compete for some silly prize money
um my team won in London
um and so we went to the finals we were
one of two student teams there and then
we got absolutely demolished we had no
chance of winning whatsoever but after
that you know I said to the PayPal
developer relations team like hey this
is the best hackathon I've ever been to
I organized hackathons myself as a
student how do I join this team
um and so they opened an internship
position for me
um and I joined as an intern and uh yeah
then after I I graduated
um and I went on to do a to start doing
a PhD in essentially programming
language design to uh because I had this
feeling that being a developer was was
Far harder than it should be and I
wanted to work on that
and then I was up there in remote
Scotland working on this PhD and was
kind of like oh wait I can get paid to
help developers instead I'm gonna go
join PayPal full time and so my path was
very very weird
yes yeah so not a lot that's applicable
there but generally speaking I would say
like the commonalities there that I
would really recommend is like
interfacing with developer communities
so
I think one of and I don't necessarily
think this is a widely held belief but I
think one of the most important things
about developer relations and why it
exists and why
um developer communities look like they
do and why we go to all these
conferences and this kind of thing is
ultimately that software engineering is
a profession with an unusual degree of
lifelong learning right because of the
pace of Technology
um software Engineers need to update
their skills and you know learn new
skills at a pace that is probably not
seen necessarily in other Industries and
other roles
and we've fight we turn to community to
help us do that but you know where else
are you going to learn about all this
new stuff well we've got the experts
speaking on it on stage our conference
right you know you don't get you don't
necessarily get hackathons for
Carpenters with like hundreds of people
sitting in a room for 24 hours to learn
how to use a new chisel right that's
something that's fairly unique to
software engineering
um
and ultimately that's kind of
the it's a very unique part about being
a software engineer
um
and participating in those communities I
think is really important for our growth
as software Engineers
um but also provides a really great
launching off point for a developer
relations person like go go find your
local Meetup go find you know go tune
into a stream for for a product you're
interested in find an open source
developer and read that blog get to know
developers around you learn new skills
and work out like how you can contribute
and I think that's probably the best
path into developer relations lots of
companies hiring for early stage trailer
for Advocates will be interested in your
technical proficiency
um and you know your ability to
communicate that technology and whatever
you know what writing and what speaking
you've already done but ultimately
they're looking for people who
understand that technology and
understand the community around that
technology who is confident in you know
talking to others in that community and
just you know Distributing a message
through that community so just go hang
out with other devs in your area is like
the easiest way nice it's a great advice
for people that want to maybe explore
this but
you're hinted at this in the beginning
of the episodes already like what is the
role of programming and how do you keep
your skill in programming up to date so
so let's first start with this first
question how important part of your job
is programming like do you ever so
program do you build prototypes do you
actually develop the products that you
work on
yeah so again this will vary super
widely depending on you know the skew of
the devrel team but generally speaking
um for a developer Advocate developer
evangelist
um being technically proficient is is
probably fairly important because it's
going to drive a lot of the content
um some developer Advocates will write
more code as part of their Outreach
efforts than others so you know some
might have live coding or demo driven
content or um or talks
um some may get directly involved in
things like the maintenance of sdks or
documentation
um but there is definitely roles within
developer relations departments to suit
kind of you know all levels of technical
proficiency I would say so you know I
said a lot of evapor relations teams are
more and more encompassing things like
documentation and developer experience
so you know there's a number of devrel
teams where it's actually the developer
relations team that own turns the sdks
or the developer facing parts of the
product
as products and they they maintain those
as products and so there will be
Engineers who are like focused on
engineering within developer relations
and you know they'll get to experience
some of what makes developer relations
unique in terms of the positioning to
the customer and being in touch with
developers and incorporating developer
feedback more directly but they're still
doing engineering so generally I would
say like working out how much
a role requires um well a role will
allow you to code or not allow you to
code it's going to come down to the job
listing and US asking some prudent
questions in the interview process I
would say developer relations if you can
find a role that is on you know if you
if you were if you are wanting to code
more finding a role where the
defibrillations team is involved in the
development of sdks or client or you
know developer facing products is is
going to be really important but there's
also a lot of fun and joy in in working
on demos and stuff I think that's I
definitely said it's very rare that
you'll get to like really plow into some
like you know scaled application Level
code but being able to just work on fun
products and churn them out and you know
find narratives to fight like find
inspiring things to build up your
company's products is is very fun
and that does lead to the question of
course of how to keep your skills
updated because your customer ultimately
also is a programmer so you have to
understand what are the challenges of
programmers today both in general and
working with programming systems but
also specifically in the tool that you
want to Market to developers how do you
keep that skill up to date specifically
you were already referring to our field
being a field in which there's lots of
learning going on
how do you manage that yeah I think it's
it's very easy to become a t-shaped
person in devrel so like it's very
because you know you're always at this
community events you're always
experimenting with new things to you
know build content it's very easy to get
very shallow experience of lots of
things
um and you know to not necessarily have
the depth to go support uh
implementation at scale another company
and so I think that's the bit that a lot
of Deborah folks struggle with I think
where
um
the best way of dealing with that for a
lot of folks is
um
well I say deal with that I mean part of
it you know part of it you can accept
that you're just not that's not your
role that like you know there's a point
where you hand that relationship off to
an architect or a sales engineer within
the organization
um but there are you know there are
other ways where like folks you know
engage in open source or they have their
pet projects
um you know for example in my current
role my role is primarily you know
um teaching new students about twilio
and that means a lot of doing the basics
like I teach them what rest apis are and
all you know all this kind of stuff
um and I certainly learned my learn a
lot myself there but you know I don't
get to go super in depth so I also have
like my pet product within our well my
not products so my pet project which is
like a demo which started as a demo but
is now starting to get quite big and I
keep adding to it and it's growing in
technical complexity which I do just to
make sure that I do still know how to do
this stuff right
um and I think that's the way a lot of
things go like you'll often find um
actually uh Brian Douglas at GitHub is a
good example of this where he's a
developer Advocate um but he's built an
incredible side project um
around helping people get into open
source but that itself is a is an app
that he is building that uses a lot of
the Technologies he's advocating and you
know has a lot of users and so he's
getting to
um it's serving his advocacy needs while
also giving him an Avenue to to build
skills yeah so the tip maybe there might
be have some sort of pet project big or
small where you can still continue to be
a developer through on the side probably
not on the main project so you can
keep your skills up to date yeah that
and I would say if you are concerned
about not writing enough code keep an
eye like keep an eye on what the what
the overlap between the devil team and
product is you want to look for for
teams that are involved in SDK
development
um and ultimately if you are super
concerned about not writing enough coal
not writing enough code it's possible
that the web privacy is not a role
you'll enjoy yeah so what you are saying
is that programming is only a small part
of the job and it might be hard to even
keep enough skill to properly do your
job let alone keep your programming
skills alive for if you want to go back
if that's where you're coming from to
programming I think I say it's a very
good job for people who enjoy coding but
who would not enjoy coding nine to five
behind like nine to five full-time yeah
that makes sense let's move on to the
next topic that we want to talk about we
talked about programming we talked about
the skills that you have as a developer
Advocate but what about content
development you talked about that early
in the episode like I would write blogs
and videos and talks how much of the job
is this content creation and also there
like how do you know you're on the right
track is there a number of blog posts
you have to write or a number of
followers you have to acquire on Twitter
how does that part of the job look like
sure
um and again sorry to keep saying it
depends but it does depends we can hear
some examples of what it might look like
so for developer Africa for developer
Africa it's going to depend it's gonna
be a fairly large part of the role so
um that Outreach driven side of develop
relations you know content I said is is
very
is is a is a very effective tactic to
reach developers developers need to
constantly be looking stuff up they need
to constantly be refreshing their skills
um so creating content and getting
content in The prominent places you know
being this one stack overflow on uh
Hacker News on you know dev2 those kind
of things is is a great tactic developer
blog posts also serve a really useful
um
like entry point to
uh more technical documentation so you
know it's often a lot easier to find
blogs just due to the nature of SEO than
it is to find precise technical
documentation and so um having folks
working on blog posts can really help
developers in their you know in the life
cycle of using your products so it does
tend to take up quite a lot
um
where you
will see it having a more prominent role
um will definitely be in in platform
companies where they are trying to serve
um wide slaves to the developer
ecosystems again twilio is an
interesting example where you know
any company can use to layer your Tech
stack doesn't really matter we we're a
rest API we have wrappers all kinds of
languages and so you end up with lots of
build x with Y right like how to how to
use twilio if you're a Ruby on Rails app
and how to do how to use this product
with this language and so like those
kind of companies where you have you you
can have that x with Y formulation
um you'll have a lot of probably a lot
of blog content being made
um in terms of success and you know
measuring that success
um again there's the standard measures
like hey is this blog post being viewed
um is this blog post appearing in places
has it been successful in ranked feeds
um
but that it's hard to
translate vanity metrics into you know
actual business value unless you have an
attribution mechanism so you know do you
have a way of like do you have a free
trial or a credit based system where you
can say hey we know that some developers
uh signed up to us for the first time
because of this blog post
um or can we see like hey this blog post
is talking about a particular
um you know a particular demo
application we can see that a bunch of
developers are using that demo
application right and so you really need
to actually have a mechanism of
um looking for actual developer activity
I actually engage developers developers
actually building with the product
developers hitting your API endpoints
developers integrating the product
um and that has to be quite a holistic
part of the content like you know you
can't just like
if you want to see actual product usage
it's hard to just kind of write a high
level high level blog and then throw in
at the end and here's a demo you could
check that out if you wanted to like the
demo needs to be useful needs to be
signed they'd actually use in in like
you know experimenting with the product
needs to be on the critical path
um yeah and then the next question would
be like how do you know this thing like
how do you know what the critical path
is do you have some sort of um group of
user developers around you that gives
you feedback I know sometimes these blog
posts have this little thumbs up thumbs
down like was this content helpful to
you how do you know even if you're on
the right path I mean very often I look
for tutorials and I'm like this is none
of this is what would help me to get
started but this is really hard to know
because you're such an expert of your
own products
writing stuff for people that are not at
all knowledgeable in anything how do you
think that
yes I think this is one of the I guess
like one of the reasons why developer
relations exists as its kind of own
thing rather than just you know being a
technical writer in marketing right it's
it's that embedding of a person who's
responsible for that content in the
developer community at large you know
you have the developer Community
um who's aware of useware of your work
that you can go and say like hey is this
useful is this what you need
um
that I think is is the easiest and best
way to do that I do think
uh you know that developer relations
folks don't necessarily focus on the
educational outcomes as much or don't
consider the educational outcomes
um as important to the success of the
role as they should do that's my
personal it's my personal soapbox which
I go to defrocon with on a regular basis
and is why I work on things like papers
we love
um so I do think that that can sometimes
be neglected but in general you know
like
being in conversation with with the
developer Community is a core function
of the role and so if you if you know if
a develop relations person is writing
content without feedback from the
community
um some part of the cycle has is not
working as intended there so I
definitely think that's that you know
whether you call it a focus group
whether it's just you know a group of
folks you trust on Twitter who happen to
go to the same conferences as you that
group that that input does need to exist
for the role to function and probably
that very much depends as you're saying
you've said a bunch of times right it
depends it depends on the type of
company your products whether you need
that is a focus group or people that you
should hang out with naturally you share
a Discord with right yeah so like the
more Enterprise you focus things for
example will have customer advisory
boards um and they will have like you
know more intentionally structured focus
group like setups again open source has
that as well open source you'll often
have
um like a council for lack of a better
word of uh like larger use users of the
open source project to sorry when a when
a company is use has when a company has
an open source project that they use
that they maintain and they will often
have not saying you know if you're an
open source maintainer you're not
running your own Council or people use
your product but if you're a company
using open source you often have uh like
an open source guiding steering body
um who may also input as well
let's move on to the public speaking
part of the job right so that is a
different form of content creation but
also it's its own thing
how do you go about finding conferences
do you like regular people do you like
submit to a call for papers or sessions
or is there a different process if
you're a developer Advocate that you use
to get yourself or your products into
conferences
so how do you find conferences there's
definitely something that's changed over
time like the Halcyon Days of lanyard
which were honestly I think probably the
best like time for funding conferences
there's all kinds of aggregators often
again like every developer relations
person has their kind of pet conferences
that they know from their Community like
you know often people get into devrel
through being visible in the community
and that will be through these events
and then you know there comes there is a
part of the cycle where it's like okay
it's time to go do my cfps for the year
I'm gonna go find conferences that are
addressing these themes these topics and
you submit to them the actual strategy
for submitting talks lots of people go
about it different ways so for example
so to put a blunt like submitting to
cfps is a numbers game right like cfp uh
so calls for papers the way that
conferences take talk submissions and
the way that they accept them those
processes can be driven differently in
lots of different ways but there's
fundamentally gonna be someone reviewing
them you're going to be up against other
really talented speakers and there's
so much content out there and so many
conferences out there so generally to
make sure that you can stay busy
throughout the year you're going to be
submitting to a lot of them and you're
going to be looking at probably getting
accepted to a lot fewer than you submit
to so people can approach that in
different ways I think this is one of
the earliest points of stress or
frustration or burnout that
developerations people
hit where they're like they look at a
conference and they craft a bespoke talk
for that conference and they do that 30
times and then 10 get accepted and
that's very sad and stressful and you've
put a lot of work in so I think what
tends to happen is people will kind of
work on you know their talks for the
year two to three talks for the year
they'll find appropriate forums for
those talks and they'll submit them and
they'll see what happens how are you
submit to developer Advocate to is a you
know and what role the product has in
that is again an always a tension point
we are embedded in our communities we
are part of those communities we want
our content we do to be valuable we
don't just want to go do ads everywhere
but you know bills need to be paid so
working out how you can represent your
company in a way that's useful for
developers is always tricky lots of
conferences will have sponsored tracks
and often that is just the best thing to
do right if you can if you need to
communicate company message you need to
do the product demo and there's a way
where you can you know Clearly say this
is a product demo no one is being
tricked into attending this everyone
knows what they're getting when they
come here if they're interested they can
come here but they know we've paid for
this slot this is going to be about the
company that's great if you're a develop
Advocate who works on a product that has
interesting parallel things to talk
about so you know you get to talk about
your products your company's technology
and how they build the things they do
and it's not just like use our product
that's also really great well sometimes
you could just be really lucky and you
work on a product that's just
interesting to developers regardless of
whether it's a demo right like
kubernetes and react to good examples
we're like you can just go talk about
how to do something in kubernetes and if
you happen to work for someone who sells
kubernetes like okay that's fine you can
do that talk right I think the the key
to submitting talks is like make sure
you're actually contributing value make
sure it's a scalable process because you
need to be doing it a lot and make sure
that you're not going to be surprising
the attendees of the conference that
they are expecting to see what they're
going to see and that they're not gonna
think there's been a rug pull with the
content they've seen and what you've
actually presented yeah like they
accidentally run into an ad like oh
right this isn't like I'm not learning
just I'm being told something yeah yeah
absolutely that's a really hard line to
walk yeah of course and some folks do it
better than others but and I think this
is even true for developers talking
about product if they're not developer
relations persons right sometimes people
get really excited I love this cool
thing I build then it also might sound
like an ad even though they're not
literally selling something it's like oh
I built this platform and then well
we'll just like you know if it's a
technology they're using that they
really like it can be really easy to
accidentally derail your conference talk
into you know just kind of selling a
technology that like you know where to
whether it's appropriate for someone
else it's gonna depend
um and it's not really the useful part
of the talk but yeah yeah so and then
that process does to me sound a lot like
other people that are submitting
conference talks right you have to
develop it a little bit yes it'll be all
too sad if it's uh if it's rejected so
it doesn't sound too different from we
have had other episodes that we will
link to about public speaking and how to
get into public speaking more in general
and that seems to talk about a quite
similar process
so so far we've very much talked about
the outside like the outgoing part of
being developer relationships person but
what about the inward part right within
the company I imagine you have
interactions with everyone like with
developers in the company with marketing
with sales with HR maybe even if you're
also doing this like hiring facing part
of the job what does that look like for
you and what does it look like in
general the type of collaborations you
have within your own company sure so
yeah in in an ideal situation there'll
be lots of these overlaps so like the
these overflaps tend to come into play
when you have a business function in the
company that needs to be in touch with
developers in some way it's really
useful to have a develop relations
person in the room because that develop
relations person is going to be you know
a representative of the developers they
are in those communities they know what
they want they know how they feel about
the company and they are a good you know
Vibe check and steering bodies so that
plays a Hell in different ways in
different companies and is you know some
companies only some departments to
overlap some won't the biggest way
you'll see this play out if you're
trying to get into devrel is when you
see uh you know what is the reporting
structure for developer relations Is it
a standalone Department very rarely it
will often report into marketing or into
engineering and you know where it sits
in the company you can tell you a lot
about those overlaps the most common
overlaps are definitely marketing
marketing is probably marketing and
Engineering are like you know the most
significant ones marketing will be
because you know as we've spoken about a
lot with some of the most prominent
roles in developer relations there's a
lot of outward facing you know Outreach
and awareness building and you know you
have a role in The Funnel engineering
will come around from the other end of
the feedback loop so you know you'll be
developer relations will have an overlap
with engineering because they're just
getting a lot of feedback directly from
developers they're talking to the people
using the product and so it's important
to have a way that that makes it into
engineering you know sales will often be
involved for a very similar reason I've
had roles particularly at GitHub where
you know I got involved in the sales
cycle all just because you know I
happened to be a technical public-facing
person in the region right so like I
quite often ended up talking to oh well
I was particularly focused on
educational use cases and I was focused
on students but because I knew the
educational use case I'd get brought in
to chat to a university that wanted to
buy a GitHub Enterprise right and that
kind of thing and so that's also fairly
common the other I think as we've spoken
a little bit about Talent as well that
will often come into play just because
again developer relations people are in
the community so they know that people
are looking for jobs they're going to
places where people are looking for jobs
people look for jobs at these events and
so if you have jobs if your company's
hiring jobs and you enjoy you where you
work it's always very nice to be able to
say hey you've just watched me do a talk
if you liked this talk come work with us
right it's very easy to do that I think
where
it can get most tricky is with ownership
and attribution though because you
overlap with so many departments you end
up having a stake in lots of things but
though it can be difficult to
integrate that overlap into your own
measures for success or how you're
evaluated right so like you know if I'm
evaluated on
a number of developers that sign up to
the platform my relationship with Talent
probably isn't helping that right so
anything I do for talent isn't
necessarily helping or if I spend a lot
of time supporting an individual
customer that's not necessarily
contributing to that numbers so I think
this is where the overlap where there is
some tension for for devrel in building
relationships lots of departments is
they often are a service provider
internally they provide something lots
of departments want but it's hard to
quantify that value with all these
different you know you might get thanked
you might get recognized by those
departments but just lots of little
tidbits here and there doesn't
necessarily make a cohesive internal
narrative yeah so everyone might like
you as a as an employee because you're
helping everyone
yeah exactly so we talked about sales
and marketing but he also briefly
mentions engineering and I want to go
like a little bit deeper there because
in a sense maybe you are also sometimes
the first customer of some products that
the system that your your company is
building right if if they build an API
you know maybe you're the first one to
try the API in the process of working
against it making a blog post about
using the API that is maybe you are
there like yeah as the first customer
maybe also fixing bugs what typically is
the relationship that all of you have
within Engineering in companies or
within programming or developers so what
you just describe to be the ideal
situation I'll tell you that does not
often play out and that's mostly just
because the pressure to ship so you know
we spoke about increasingly developer
facing companies want to you know do the
big splashy launch at the annual
conference and in those cases things are
always against the deadline like the
conference date is the Target and so
there's often not not as long an
internal period to play with things as
you would as you would hope or as a
developer relations person needs but in
the ideal world that is the situation
you know if developer relations gets
involved in the content for a product
launch and this is actually I'd actually
say this is probably more an overlap
with product marketing than it is with
engineering because that will usually be
how that relationship happens right so
for the for the blog post to end up
being written by developer release like
the pre-launch blog post or the
pre-launch demos to be written by
developer relations they're probably
being involved in like a product
marketing effort right but yeah having
that Avenue into product managers and
being able to say like hey I played with
you know the pre-release version here's
the friction I had it's very valuable I
think
nowadays especially and I do think
companies like GitHub have kind of made
this commonplace nowadays you will often
have protracted public Alphas that deal
with that part like you know the
internal pre-release cycle of it so
often same we'll go live on the public
Alpha and developer experience issues
will get ironed out then and developer
relations people will be very important
in that cycle because again they're
they're an Avenue for feedback they'll
probably be promoting the alpha they'll
be communicating with folks during the
alpha but in terms of being the first
customer I think that is relatively
uncommon for the reasons I mentioned oh
this is a busy because yeah as you're
saying that would be a nice trajectory
where first you test it sort of
internally and maybe some of the fixes
you can even make yourself whereas
regular customers outside of the company
of course it would be harder for them to
iron out little issues in enough yeah it
often comes and again like
someone will hear this and say that you
know they are contrary to the point and
that they are the first customer but I
think the engineering collaborations
tend to come after first exposure to the
public it will be a developer has gotten
hold of the API and has feedback and
that will get back in to engineering via
a developer Advocate that will often be
the relationship with engineering it
will be the other end of the feedback
cycle and it'll be there the people who
the first customers come to rather than
being the first customers themselves
yeah that makes total sense
suppose people that are listening are
interested in exploring such a career
what are some of the resources I guess
like if you want to learn a new
programming language we sort of all know
what are the paths toward that one thing
I think you already mentioned was
something called devrelconf like a
conference specifically is that a good
place to get started or do you have
books blogs videos to explore this path
so defrocon is a developerations
conference organized by a consultancy
called hoopy it's Matthew Revel it is
wonderful it's a conference for Deborah
practitioners I would not necessarily
recommend shelling out and attending it
if you're not yet in devrel but if
you're interested in devrel but what I
would recommend doing is going to over
to the YouTube channel going to
developerrelations.com and checking out
the enormous backlog of videos all the
talks have been recorded you can find
them all there have been you know the
conference has been running a long time
now and it is for devrel practitioners
so there's a lot of stuff in depth there
that's probably not super useful if
you're just starting out but there has
been additions of the conference focused
on early in career developer relations
folks and getting into industry so
you'll definitely find those talks I
think other really great resources Mary
fengvel's newsletter American girl has a
wonderful newsletter that also often
includes job posts ultimately I think
the best thing you can do though is to
go and choose a developer product you
like choose an API you like choose a
tool you like and hit the landing page
and pretend you've never seen it before
and put yourself in the mindset of a
developer who is assessing this tool to
see if they should use it at work and go
through that journey and see if like see
what you think see how quick it takes
you to make your first API requests see
what friction you hit see what docs you
think aren't quite clear enough and
having done that process like distill
those thoughts write something down and
then reflect and say like hey did I
enjoy doing that I might be a developer
relations person that would be what I
would recommend Ah that's a great way to
get started and of course some of the
skills that we talked about also as I
already said have been covered in other
episodes It's so technical writing or
becoming a public speaker if you would
want to work on some of those subscales
some of our older episodes might also
help and other resources to work
specifically on those different skills
one thing I'd caution on that a little
well sorry I say caution it's I think
getting into develop relations sometimes
can fall into the same trap as getting
into software engineering like you know
lots of people say oh go contribute to
loads of Open Source that's a good way
to get into software engineering right
or like and I think the same can kind of
happen to devra where it's like it's
very easy to say go give a load of talks
but like they take a lot of time and
work and not everyone can afford to do
that as part of their career change
there are definitely you know there will
be job listings out there that say like
hey we want you to have this many
Twitter followers and have done this
many talks but there is job roles out
there for early in career devil people
where they will just look at the
experience you have as a software
engineer and won't have required you to
do the job of a devrel before you're a
devrel right so if you see job postings
that you know require you to do a load
of Labor you don't have time to do in
the career switch don't be discouraged
jobs do exist for like early early
career devrel jobs do exist ah great
well this is a very good advice I think
that's most of the things I wanted to
talk about do you think there's anything
we miss any angle about this part of the
job that you still want to talk about I
don't think so I think your questions
are very far thank you fantastic thank
you so much so then what about you
suppose audience wants to follow you
like what are the best place to stay up
to date with the work that you are doing
sure so I'm jna underscore sh on Twitter
and you'll probably find me if you just
searched Joe Nash we were added to the
show notes as well perfect if you are
interested in developer education that's
where I spend a lot more time nowadays I
run a Meetup called papers we love
education which is a paper reading group
for Computer Science Education papers
and I work on an educational game called
twilio quest so I recommend checking
those out as well yeah so definitely add
those links to the show notes so people
can check them out thanks for being on
the show today thank you so much for
having me
[Music]
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc.radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening